בוקר
טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ק Kuf 100.
Before we start I should just mention that I assume by now
people have heard that Belda Lindenbaum passed away yesterday. The funeral was
a small funeral, it was family only which really speaks to, I
think it's a testament to her because if it was a, it
could have been tens of thousands of people there and with all
of her public roles, I mean she really prioritized family above all.
And she was a woman who people were posting on Facebook the
other day, so many posts about women who said that all the
תורה Torah knowledge they have was because of institutions that she had
really funded and that she had enabled to happen. So really shows
you what philanthropy and particularly guided philanthropy and somebody with a real
vision can do to change the face of the Jewish community. So
it's really a terrible loss for her family and for כלל ישראל.
Klal Yisrael. I think she was 76.
So really her memory should be for a blessing.
Okay, so we pick up on the משנה Mishna on צט עמוד
ב, Tzadi Tet Amud Bet, the bottom of the page and we
read the following. So we're dealing again with the widow selling off
the estate in order to pay off the כתובה Ketubah and we've
dealt with the question about if she oversells or undersells and from
there we had a whole discussion about the type of she's seen
as a שליח Shaliach of the orphans and from there we had
a whole discussion about what do you call it? About the general
latitude that a שליח Shaliach has. Now, I did want to say
something. I had been miscorrectly when it spoke about her selling something
worth a מנה Maneh and a דינר Dinar for only a מנה,
Maneh, I had been saying 125 because a golden דינר Dinar is
25 זוז. Zuz. However, רש"י Rashi in a number of places, once
in a previous סוגיא, Sugya, said oh, it's only a דינר, Dinar,
it's not even a, it's a very small percentage.
And that's gonna also, he repeats that here and that's clear here
as well. And it seems that we're talking here about a silver
דינר, Dinar, which is essentially a זוז, Zuz, which is really just
one unit. So it's important to revise understanding today's דף Daf but
also what we've been talking about before when it spoke about her
underselling or selling too much property where she sold something for 101
for only 100 or she sold a piece of property worth 101
for 101. Those were the two scenarios the גמרא Gemara dealt with
before but we're really talking about a trivial difference, a 1% difference.
And it gets back to Rachel's point about how much latitude do
you give somebody, right? So it's important to appreciate that we were
talking about a very small difference, not the way I framed it
yesterday. And with that in mind let's look at this
next משנה. Mishna. שום הדיינים. Shum HaDayanim. Now if the judges, she
didn't do it on her own but she did it through the
court and the courts came in and they assessed the property. שפיחתו
שתות או הוסיפו שתות. Shepikhsu Shtu'sh O Osifu Shtu'sh. If they were
off by a sixth, which usually means a fifth because a fifth,
if something's worth 100 and you make a difference of a fifth
which is 20, the difference of 120 is now a sixth of
the total at the end although it doesn't work the same way
if you go down by a sixth. So we won't work exactly
how to do the math. But anyway if it's more or less
than a שתות Shtush if they're off by that much, מכרן בטל,
Mekhan Batel, it's void. Now again a שתות Shtush is normally the
amount that you have to be off for אונאה Ona'ah for overcharging
or undercharging that also voids the sale except there's no אונאה Ona'ah
for קרקעות. Karka'ot. So if it was just an issue and this
is the point we saw yesterday as well, it was just an
issue of the rules of אונאה, Ona'ah, it would always be valid.
But it's not just an issue of אונאה. Ona'ah. It's not the
owner that is selling it him or herself. It's that somebody is
doing it for the orphans, either the court or the judges. And
therefore they might be seen as stepping outside of their authority to
make such a to sell it with such a so much off
of its original value. So here what the משנה Mishna is implicitly
saying is up to a sixth it's still binding but once it
gets to a sixth or more then they're stepping outside of their
authority and then it's not binding. And in that way it's contrasted
to what the previous משנה Mishna said about the widow where again,
now correcting from what I said yesterday, the widow even if she's
off by
1%, it was worth 101 and she sold it for 100. She
undersold it by 1%. It's void. Whereas here it's void only if
it's significantly off. So then רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
no, מכרן קיים, Mekhan Kayam, even if they're off by that much
it's still valid. Why? Why? שאם כן מה כח בית דין יפה?
She-im ken mah ko'ach beit din yafeh? Which שאם כן she-im ken
sort of means like אם לא כן, im lo ken, but if
you don't say this then where's the power... of the court, you
know, the power of the court, the court has authority, it does
something, it's binding. If you start reassessing it, you know, you could
sort of basically look at this as a type of a public
policy statement, right? If you had to constantly re- you know say
oh no all right we have to reverse it because the court
was so off, it undermines their authority, okay? To reverse it. Or
you could say the other way, the court has such authority, I
mean if you base- you know if you could say like הפקר
בית דין הפקר Hefker Beis Din Hefker and you know pretty much
what the court says goes most of the time. They're the ultimate
authori- you know the court defines what the legal realities are by
their rulings. So it's you know by by fiat, yes, that makes
it a binding sale. Now תוספות Tosafos has an interesting question whether
okay the sale is binding but would you have to pay back
the overage? There are cur- you know like by אונאה onaah there
are two separate questions: one is is the sale void, the other
is the sale might be binding, like for let's say it was
a case where there was laws of אונאה. onaah. It wasn't קרקע.
karka. I sold you my car, it was a brand new car
so it was a clear value you know you just go ahead
now on the internet you can do some price shopping and comparison
or whatever and afterwards you find out that I overcharged you by
10 percent, not enough for it to be אונאה. onaah. So the
sale is still binding, but you might still be in a position
to say you have to give me back the 10 percent, that
was a clear overcharge, okay? So here there's תוספות Tosafos asks that
same question: it's one thing to say that the court is so-
has the power, they did the sale, you don't reverse it, but
maybe there still is an idea of reversing the overage. That's not
clear. You know again it might also have to do with are
you concerned about undermining their authority, maybe even reversing the overage is
a type of an undermining of their authority, not clear from the
משנה mishnah what you would say, but certainly it has more power
than when she is selling it where even a little bit of
a change it is בטל. batel. Now we end with saying אבל
aval and this is presumably going back to
the חכמים chachamim אם עשו איגרת ביקורת ביניהם im asu igheret bikoret
beineihem
as they did a writ of assessment that's probably what it
means לבקר levaker לא lo you
know ביקורת תהיה bikoret tihyeh an inspection an assessment. So they basically
did it between
them אפילו מכרו שווה מנה במאתיים afilu machru shaveh maneh bemasatayim even
if they were way off. The seller? What? No, the court. Now
it's interesting the phrase letter and between them. What does letter mean?
Why doesn't it say you know it really means like it might
mean like that they've done a document, תוספות Tosafos says you know
letter might mean a letter from one court to the next but
it doesn't seem like there are two courts here. So it so
it seems like it's a little bit funny what the phrase means
but essentially means when they they went through an official process of
assessing its value and writing it up, then even the חכמים chachamim
agree that even if they're way off it's still binding. Beineihem you
mean the members of the בית דין? beis din? Yeah, sounds like
it, yes. אפילו מכרו שווה מנה במאתיים afilu machru shaveh maneh bemasatayim
even if they were way off, they sold 100 for 200, או
שווה מאתיים במנה o shaveh masatayim bemaneh or 200 for
100 right מכרן קיים mechran kayam it's still a binding sale. Again
whether there has to be any returning of the overage is not
stated. The פשט pshat of the משנה mishnah is that there doesn't
have to be any returning of the overage, it's done and you're
done with it. Now of course if they sold it for too
high of a price the buyer wants- wants to reverse it, right?
The orphans and the widow are totally fine, less of the estate
was sold and the widow's pocketing her money and they- they're happy.
But it's the buyer who wants reverse it. If they undersold it
then it's the sellers who want to reverse it. I mean probably
the widow doesn't care too much but the orphans care, okay but
in all these cases it's saying that if it's more than a
sixth according to the חכמים, chachamim, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says it's always binding. More than a sixth or more
it's- it's בטל batel unless there was this איגרת ביקורת. igheret bikoret.
Now רש"י Rashi says איגרת ביקורת igheret bikoret does not just mean
they called in an assessor and they wrote it up. I mean
how also would it have gotten so far off and why does
that necessarily mean that all of a sudden now it's more binding?
So if you look at רש"י Rashi and this is based on
what we're going to see in the גמרא, gemara, רש"י Rashi says
הכרזה, hachrazah, okay? ולשון ביקורת שמבקרין אותו בני אדם על ידי הכרזה.
u'leshon bikoret shemevakrin oto
bnei adam al yedei hachrazah. It doesn't mean they went ahead and
did an assessment and brought in an assessor but they did a-
they you know they make it an announcement they did a- like
a public auction, right? Don't they do that when you you know
you have an estate you have to take out ads in the
newspapers, right? You have to make it known so that that's how
you ensure that you get a good price is that you- you
let everybody know and everybody comes in and they bid or whatever
and it's through that process you're ensuring that you're getting the best
price.
So that's what it is, the people are doing the ביקורת, bikoret,
not the בית דין, beis din, by them coming and assessing it
and you know being part of the auction. So if somehow everybody
misjudged it, okay, you know, I mean you did all that you
could have reasonably done and that's nobody's fault in that case and
then it is binding. You know maybe that self-defines what the price
is, you know the price determined by ultimately how do you know
objectively what a price is? If that's what the market has determined
at that time even if it was way off maybe that is
the price. Okay there were some questions, Bobby you had a question,
Michael you had a question, no, okay, so you wait long enough
all your questions are answered.
Yes, so if it's this difficult to assess land, how
could they meaningfully get the difference between 100 דינרים dinarim and- I
could see maybe a difference between 100 and 125, but the difference
between 100 and 101, how could they...
yeah I mean that's a very good point, like when the
משנה... mishnah... But if he undersold it, it's בטל batel. *batel*, I
mean,
unless of course the difference goes towards paying off her כתובה kesubah
*ketubah*. But if there's no כתובה *ketubah* left to pay off, then
it's בטל *batel*. Right, how do you determine what it means that
it undersold? Like, how do you—I mean, it's true. It must mean,
I mean, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to get to it
a little bit. It must mean similar to what we said yesterday
about and we're going to repeat in a minute about the guy
who took תרומה terumah, *terumah* and 1/50th is the norm, but if
anywhere between 1/40th and 1/60th, it's still good. There must be like
the terms like some range, like somebody would come and say, it's
sort of like the blue book value of a car, right? You
got the high end of the range and the low end of
the range. And presumably she's over, she's under from even the lowest
end of the range. You have to imagine it's something like that.
But you're right, given that there's אינו לקרקעות *eino la-karka'os* has a
lot to do, I mean, it's a formal exclusion, but that's a
lot to do with the impossibility of setting a precise value on
it and determining a market price, then how could we speak about
her underselling and it be מכר בטל *mecher batel* because of her
role as a שליח shaliach *shaliach*? So I don't know the real
answer. Okay, but it's got to have something to do with the
fact that we assume that there's some range and that she's—I mean,
this is what I would guess
is, but I can't prove this, and that she goes less even
than the low end of the range. All right, but it's a
really good question. So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*.
This idea of אינו לקרקעות *eino la-karka'os* accomplishes, but the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* will range back that you said that maybe the whole market
price misestimated, but also sometimes individuals have things like sentimental value or
there's some factor that doesn't apply to other people. So if despite
the fact that everybody else is only willing to pay 100, she's
willing to pay 150, there may be a reason for that as
long as the process
is transparent.
That's interesting for the case where they're saying it was undersold, the
court is saying in your eyes it was undersold, but not right.
That's a good point. Okay. איבעיא להו *iba'ya lehu*. So they ask
the question. And this is very interesting how the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
sort of wanted to take from these very concrete cases about the
widow and the orphans and they want to ask more generically about
what does this tell you about שליחות shlichus *shlichus*, about agency and
being appointed and empowered to sell something and to buy something. So
that's the questions we were asking the other day, right? Remember, if
the שליח shaliach *shaliach* does more than he was told or less
than he was told. Okay, now we're going to say the same
type of a question. What can we get from our משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* about a rule about a שליח shaliach, *shaliach*? So let's take
a look. שליח shaliach
כמאן *shaliach keman*? I go ahead, just like we talked about yesterday,
I make Michael my שליח shaliach *shaliach* and say, Michael, sort of
like I keep on thinking about
the story about Jack and the Beanstalk. Jack, go to the market
and sell
Bessie. He winds up selling for some beans. Okay, so I say
Michael sell my plot of land and he goes and he sells
it, and he sells it a little bit well—for me I would
care if it's a little bit less than its true market value,
right? How much, this is really going back to yesterday's question. Yesterday's
issue wasn't a focus on selling it for too little or too
more, although the primary question yesterday was selling more land than you
should have sold or less land than you should have sold. Now
we're going to focus on if Michael didn't get as good of
a price as he could have gotten. How off is he and
he's still acting as my שליח shaliach *shaliach* or not? Okay, so
let's take a look. גמרא gemara *Gemara* sort of did discuss it
yesterday if you remember, got to it towards the end, but now
we're going to revisit it. Okay. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says
like this, איבעיא להו *iba'ya lehu*. שליח shaliach. כמאן *shaliach keman*? Who,
which category do we put him in? Because we now have two
categories of somebody representing the heir's estate with different rules: the category
of the אלמנה almanah *almanah*, that when she's the widow that even
a little bit off, it's void, and the category of the בית
דין beis din, *beis din*, that only when they're a sixth off
is it void. So who is the שליח shaliach *shaliach* like in
this case?
You didn't tell me how much to sell it for.
Right, exactly. And you—and it turns out that I did then. Right,
exactly. Or maybe I did and you said look, I couldn't get
anybody to get your price but I got it for a little
bit less, maybe something like that. How much off? Right. So שליח
shaliach? כמאן *shaliach keman*? רבא אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman: שליח shaliach?
כדיינים *Rava amar Rav Nachman shaliach k'dayanim*, like when the court sells
it. As long as they're within a sixth of the price, it's
still valid. רב שמואל בר ביסנא אמר רב נחמן Rav Shmuel Bar
Bisna amar Rav Nachman, כאלמנה ke'almanah. *Rav Shmuel bar Bisna amar Rav
Nachman k'almanah*. No, like the widow sells it, and even if they're
a tiny bit off, it's void. All right. So רבא אמר רב
נחמן Rav Nachman שליח shaliach, כדיינים *Rava amar Rav Nachman shaliach k'dayanim*,
like the court. מה דיינים לא לדידהו אף שליח shliach נמי לא
לדידיה *Ma dayanim lo l'didhu af shaliach nami lo l'didei*. The court
isn't selling it for their own sake, right? They're doing it for
somebody else, they have no vested interest. So
therefore like we give them a little bit more latitude. You can't—right,
there's no concern that somebody's going
to somehow have some deal
going, or they're just doing it as a—and maybe it's also the
issue that some people were asking yesterday, who would ever want to
be a שליח shliach *shaliach* if you have to deal with all
this headache? So there's a little bit more tolerance for being off.
I did you a
favor. doesn't necessarily mean, I mean it could mean that we're a
little bit afraid she's got some side deal going, right? Like I'll
sell it to you, I'll undersell it to you and you'll give
me a little like kickback, right? We could always worry about the
side deal problem. Okay, but beyond that, she's enough self-motivated to do
it that we can be more demanding on her. You know, she's
going to be doing it anyway, she's got to do it for
whatever, so we can demand from her greater care and greater, you
know, and greater precision. Okay, so he says the שליח shliach is
like a third party, like a בית דין, beis din we give
the שליח shliach? a little bit more latitude. רב שמואל בר ביסנא
אמר רב נחמן, Rav Shmuel Bar Bisna amar Rav Nachman, now רב
שמואל בר ביסנא Rav Shmuel Bar Bisna says in the name of
רב נחמן: Rav Nachman
Is this just for קרקע karka though that we're saying this?
Well, yeah, I mean if it wasn't, well, yeah, I mean קרקע
karka allows us to ask it as a very open-ended question because
we don't have to worry about how אונאה ona'ah would intersect with
this question. Okay, רב שמואל Shmuel, בר ביסנא אמר רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman כאלמנה. Nope,
the שליח shliach is like an אלמנה almanah and therefore it's very
precise and even a little bit off, it's void. מה אלמנה יחידה
אף שליח יחידה. mah almanah yechidah af shaliach yechidah.
It's an individual and therefore the real rule should go like even
a little bit off, you're not my שליח, shliach, that's the standard
in anybody that has a status of a normal person, that's the
rule. It's only בית דין Beis din as a special status because
of their power of the court that it's valid even when they
even when they overstep their bounds. Okay, אף שליח יחיד לאפוקי בית
דין דרבים נינהו. af shaliach yachid l'apokei beis din d'rabbim ninhu. בית
דין beis din, is like, you know, is like many people, but
not just many, it means they're, you know, they're a institutional body
and they represent authority. So therefore even if we reject רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel, who says that it's always valid by בית דין, beis
din we still say that the power of בית דין beis din,
is that it's valid in a wider range. They have that authority
behind them, so it's valid in a wider range.
Normal person objective so to speak?
No, no, I don't think, you could say objective, you know what,
you know what, that's interesting. No, no, vested was the earlier point.
No, that's a good point and I wasn't thinking about that, that
רבים rabbim is the idea that it's not one, one person, you
know, I wasn't thinking about that at all but you're right, that
could fit very well the phrase of יחיד ורבים. yachid v'rabbim. That
one person could get way off, like one person could really not
know what they're doing and be way off, whereas a בית דין,
beis din you know, you have three people, hopefully that averages out
somehow, you know, the assessment, although I know that they've done studies
where, you know, that we tend to think that groups will make
more sort of like moderate down the center middle of the road
decisions than individuals and they find out that that's not true. But
anyway, that's, but I'm not sure that's true because if that were
true, then the question would be how likely is it that they're
off or not off? That's not the question we're asking. We're asking
the question of if they're off, is it still
binding? So, I think it's more, I mean, I have to think
about your approach more, but I think it's more just that בית
דין beis din is just a special, you know, a special entity.
It's an entity that has power and therefore even if we don't
go as far as רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, we're going to say
it's going to be binding, you know, it's valid what they've done
in a wider range of cases.
It's not a process question, it's status.
Well, the reason that they're author-, you know, look, you could also
look at it as like is it a private deal or not?
I tell Michael to go sell my thing, right? It's all about
my empowering him. So I could say, I didn't want you to
undersell it for one dollar, and I did not empower you for
that purpose. And that's about our private deal, so you overstep your
boundaries, I didn't make you an agent. Whereas בית דין beis din
comes and we are selling it for the orphans, it doesn't really
matter as much what the orphans wanted, right? It's they have the
power to represent the orphans, so that gives them more latitude, even
if it goes outside of the bounds. I think that's more what
it's saying. Okay, so that's the question. והלכתא שליח כאלמנה v'hilchasa shaliach
ke'almanah that the שליח shliach, is like the אלמנה and even a
tiny little going under, it's void. Now I got to tell you,
I want to tell you something ironic here. It sounds like, oh
my God, that's so unfair, even a little under it's void. You
know who this benefits? Benefits the seller, right? Like I said yesterday,
when the גמרא gemara said, oh no, if the שליח shliach, makes
a mistake, it's not good. Oh, but there's no אונאה ona'ah by
קרקע? karka? That's when you sell it yourself. But if a שליח
shliach is selling it, then they're overstepping their bounds and they're not
my שליח. shliach So great, anytime I want to sell land and
I want to make sure that I don't get cheated, that I
don't, I go through a שליח shliach and if he's off even
by a dollar, then it's void. Okay, now, of course, the question
could be that, and here's an interesting question that the גמרא Gemara
doesn't explore, which is if it's over sold, right? Then I'm
happy for him to get a higher price, right? So and if
there's no אונאה ona'ah by קרקע, karka, like I'm happy for Michael
to, whatever good price you can get, you can sell twice the
goods in today. What is the guy going to say? He wasn't
your שליח? shliach Who says he wasn't my שליח? shaliach I'm happy
for him to be my שליח, shaliach right? So it would really
only make sense to be void if it was undersold. And the
משנה Mishnah though says, the משנה mishnah doesn't say otherwise. but it
does say when בית דין beis din oversells by a sixth, it
is void. So it's not clear why when בית דין beis din
oversold it was void, maybe because בית דין beis din is not
just representing the orphans. בית דין beis din has to be responsible
for for everybody. So if they're doing something that's not fair in
a significant way to another party, then that would be then very
interesting that under one hand בית דין beis din it would be
valid in a wider range of cases, but it would be that
but the difference would be that when בית דין beis din sells
it for too much, it would be void, and when my שליח
sells it for too much, I see no evidence in anything that
it would be void. Why should it be void? He sold it
for too much, it wasn't rules of אונאה, ona'ah, good going Michael,
I'm making you my שליח next time. So that's interesting too to
appreciate that בית דין's Beis Din overselling might have might be more
void than a שליח because they're responsible for everyone. But again the
point is, why not everybody should just be smart and sell their
קרקע karka through a שליח? Okay, because then if it's if it
they can never be cheated and undersold.
Yes, שליח does cost money.
Well maybe I pay him, maybe he's my friend, maybe he's maybe
he's currying favor, you know particularly in the ancient world where there
was all of this patronage and people doing things you know, so
who knows what his incentive is, it's not really our business what
his incentive is. I mean you know if it was a case
of like a שליח, it was a case of like a שומר,
shomer, right? Then it's more business because then whether they're paid or
not you know affects their level of care that they're required to
have. Now like you could imagine that the same is true with
a שליח, you know, I do not know of הלכה halacha making
a distinction between the you know between paid שליחות shlichus, and unpaid
שליחות, shlichus. although you could definitely imagine that maybe the parameters should
change in terms of what is the you know to what degree
are they seen as empowered, what's the degree of latitude and so
on. But you know that's really not its concern why he's my
שליח, okay could be a million reasons. Yeah.
So as society understand, am I understanding that at that time society
understood and took it for granted that a שליח if he undersells-
sells a property could be challenged and and that's perfectly it's not
going to humiliate the שליח because that's what society-
Yeah you know what I mean, come on, business is business. I
mean I'm serious, business is business. Right? You're making this very personal
where it might have been personal, but it's also business, right? I
mean I'm a big I'm a businessman, I've got I've got all
these holdings, I'm not going to go and be involved in every
single deal, I'm going to ask you know people who my you
know people my lawyers or whatever to sell it for me, right?
And as you said there's no downside to asking.
Exactly. I mean think of a שליח as my lawyer, my lawyer's
handling the deal for me, right? So I'm paying him it doesn't
matter why I'm paying him. Of course the thing is is that
you'd only want to engage in a transaction with somebody that has
full power of attorney and that you cannot say, oh well in
this case it wasn't binding, right? So that's what makes my- how
does this work in society that I can say you know he's
authorized to sell but then I'm always able to say yeah unless
unless it wasn't what I liked then I go then I take
it away. A consiglieri. Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, ומה שנא u-mah shna says the גמרא Gemara מהא
דתנן, mei-ha de-tenan,
this is going to sound familiar from yesterday, how's it different from
that which we taught in the משנה Mishnah, האומר לשלוחו צא ותרום
תרום כדעת בעל הבית. ha-omer li-shlucho tzei ve-tarum tarum ke-da'as ba'al ha-bayis.
You tell your שליח go and take תרומה, terumah, they go they
do it according to what they estimate the owner would have done.
ואם אינו יודע דעתו של בעל הבית ve-im eino yodea da'aso shel
ba'al ha-bayis if they don't know תורם בבינונית toreim be-veinonis you do
the average which is one fiftieth אחד מחמישים echad mi-chamishim
two percent. פיחת עשרה או הוסיף עשרה picheis asarah o hosif asarah
if it's one sixtieth or one fortieth which is within the normal
range תרומתו תרומה terumaso terumah it's valid. So there you see that
you are allowed- that it's a case of an individual and you
don't have to be precise, there's a range, okay, and therefore so
that's because there is a range. Exactly. So you see you don't
have to be precise. So the גמרא Gemara says התם נמי hasam
nami כיון דאיכא דתורם בעין רעה ואיכא דתורם בעין יפה keivan de-ika
de-toreim be-ayin ra'ah ve-ika de-toreim be-ayin yaffah
some people do it generous and some people are stingy and some
people are generous, so there's a known range and everybody falls somewhere
within that bell-shaped curve at least within one standard deviation. אמר ליה
הכי אמדינך amar lei hachi amdinach I estimated that here that you
are the generous end of the range or the stingy end of
the range. אבל הכא טעותא היא aval hacha ta'usa hi here there's
an objective error. And again this gets to the question everybody's asking:
what do you mean an objective error? How do we know the
precise amount? So that's why I would say if there really is
a an objective range, like if an assessor would come and say
yeah I could see you getting anywhere between you know a hundred
and ten and a hundred and forty thousand dollars for this piece
of property, then presumably it's not a טעות ta'us until you go
below the low end of the range. I would imagine applying what
this גמרא Gemara says. One has to do with what my desire
would have been when I'm taking תרומה, the other one would have
been the גמרא Gemara says ah but here there's an objective error.
Well is it really an objective error if there's a range of
possible prices? I would imagine that you'd have to go below the
low end of the range.
The way you just framed it now is interesting. It's not like
objectively it's not knowable. You could always get an assessor to give
you an opinion. It's just that if you don't know because you
don't have an assessment. It's not like objectively it's not knowable.
You could always—Well, no, 'cause even if you—yeah,
but right, but yes, so somebody
comes and tells you the value of your house and then you
go ahead and you sell it, and if it's in a bad
market you could be dropping the price three times and you're way
below the low end of the assessor and still nobody is buying
it. And if it's in a good market you could get 50%
more.
Doesn't assessment, doesn't assessment always assume the market context?
Yeah, but
I'm telling you that's what happens in the field is that people
sometimes keep on cutting and cutting and cutting and they can't sell
the house even though its market value is something else, and then
there are times when there's such a high demand that they get
significantly more. So that's the problem, you know, how can the גמרא
Gemara talk about it like there's this objective amount? So that's what's
being asked, you know, you have to either assume some scenario where
there's a very clear—look, here's the difference, maybe and this will help
us appreciate. I imagine if we're dealing about acreage for growing wheat,
there probably is not a lot of variation. דרך כלל, Derech Klal,
right? Well, exactly, meaning, you know, it's not the same as like
location, location, location for where my house is located and what the,
you know, and so on, what community is and all those types
of things. I mean sure it matters like is it close to
a body of water or whatever, but if you imagine thousands of
acres of wheat fields, right, it probably is a pretty stable, you
know, objective price, you know? So maybe that helps us understand this
a little bit. But again, you know, who knows how precise is
it really possible to be? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, אמר רב הונא בר חיננא אמר רב נחמן הלכה כדברי חכמים.
Amar Rav Huna bar Chinana
Amar Rav Nachman, Halacha KeDivrei Chachamim. We rule like the חכמים Chachamim
that it goes by a sixth and not by רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that says it's always binding when the
בית דין Beis Din? does it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
ולית ליה לרב נחמן מה כוח בית דין יפה? V'leis lei leRav
Nachman Ma Koach Beis Din Yafeh? Does רב נחמן Rav Nachman not
hold of this principle that 'What good is the power of בית
דין?' Beis Din meaning that the בית דין's Beis Din acts are
always binding? Because he says we don't say it's always binding; more
or less than a sixth isn't good. But one minute, it seems
like רב נחמן Rav Nachman believes in that principle of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. ואמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל, Ve'amar
Rav Nachman Amar Shmuel, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says in the name
of שמואל, Shmuel יתומים שבאו לחלוק בנכסי אביהם, Yetomim shebau lachlok benichsei
avihem,
orphans come and presumably underaged orphans come to divide the estate of
their father.
בית דין מעמידים להם אפוטרופוס, Beis Din maamidim lahem apitropus, בית דין
Beis Din assigns each one of them a representative, a, ובוררים להם
חלק יפה, uborin lahem chelek yafeh, and each one of the orphan's
representatives negotiates in favor of the orphan that they're representing and they
divide the estate that way. Okay, that makes sense, right? Now, הגדילו,
higdilu, now they're adults, יכולין למחות. yecholin limchos.
Now they can say, 'Hey, I don't think my representative got me
a good deal, I object.' Okay, and they're allowed to object. Of
course, can you imagine like what, how, yeah the guardian, right, but
it's more like an executor, guardian, I mean guardian like right, anyway,
some type of court-appointed representative. Anyway, can you imagine like what what
would happen as a result of that, right? I mean even for
five years, I mean how do you, you get paralyzed if you
can reverse that after many years. Of course, how much transactions could
they have done in those five years if they're, if they're minors?
But the אפוטרופוס apitropus could have been doing transactions for them and
now we're going to reverse it all? Okay, at the point when
they get old? Okay, right. Exactly, right. So anyway that's the first
ruling. But then כי אתא רב דימי אמר, ki ata Rav Dimi
amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came, it's—I'm sorry, it says like
this, רב נחמן דידיה אמר, Rav Nachman didei amar, but רב נחמן
Rav Nachman himself disagrees with what שמואל Shmuel says and says no,
הגדילו אין יכולין למחות, higdilu ein yecholin limchos, they cannot object. אם
כן מה כוח בית דין יפה? Im ken ma koach beis din
yafeh? Because if not what good is the court-appointment of
the אפוטרופוס? apitropus? The court-appointed אפוטרופוס apitropus says this is what's going
to be and this is how we're going to divide it, and
then it's binding. I don't care if you like it or not,
I don't care if one of the אפוטרופסין apitropsin that we appointed
was—I mean you know, I guess I wonder what could happen if
you could like, if you could say like complete incompetent counsel, right?
Like you know, I mean it's very hard when people want to
appeal sentences because of you know, the claim of incompetency of counsel,
you need very strong evidence for that. Maybe that would be an
exception, but just סתם stam saying I don't like the choices that
he made for me? No, the court appointed it, it's binding, that's
the power of the court.
Okay so you—Sorry, just to clarify, this is the court appointing somebody
to look out for the minor orphan against the interest of the
widow?
No, of the other minor orphans. The other minor—There are five orphans
and we've got to divide the estate. I'm sorry if I wasn't
clear. And they're allowed to divide the estate between them.
Each one gets a separate, gets a separate representative, and those representatives
work it out.
But there's also a widow?
Not—in this—it's irrelevant for this discussion.
Well, but
I
think what's been bothering me this whole week is this idea that
there is a,
there is an assumption that the widow, that what's good
for
the
widow—
Right, so I would say that,
I don't think it is true that some of the scenarios we're
dealing is when they are in sort
of conflict when there is a conflict of interest. I think it's
not correct that the גמרא Gemara is saying that their interests are
always at loggerheads. It's just dealing with the reality that sometimes they
are and dealing with how those would play out. If those are
the cases we're talking about, I understand why you get the impression
that it's sounding like that's always the case. But we're not saying
that. We're just saying in a scenario where she over-sold or under-sold
their property, then that creates a conflict of interest about what's going
to happen. But I don't think we're suggesting and it is true,
okay, you're right. I mean, we also talked about she wants to
be supported by the estate. So there are areas where, right, there
are areas where...
The death of the husband...
I understand. But you know what? You know what? If, like, if
you go ahead and you want to work out your divorce
settlement with a what is it, an arbitrator, then that's... then there's
nothing interesting for us to discuss. You work it out, it's not
our interest. Meaning, the interesting cases are when there is a conflict
of interest. It's not saying there is always a conflict of interest,
those are the cases we have to talk about.
A divorce is different because the husband is still alive and...
Forget the analogy. Forget the divorce. My point is, is that yes,
the גמרא Gemara is only talking about cases of conflict of interest,
because those are the interesting cases. Cases where everybody is happy and
working together are not cases we have to discuss. But you're right,
it does skew a perspective about it.
Towards the perspective towards the heirs who are men.
I don't think that's correct. I really don't. I think the heirs
could all be women. If they're all girls and they also are
heirs to the estate, it's the exact same issue. Okay?
So divvying it to the heirs...
I don't see divvying... okay, we have to talk about that some
other time. I really don't see it that way. I see that
there were different interests on the table and we're trying to figure
out how to do it.
I understand how it creates an impression that they're always at loggerheads,
but we're just... no, those are the interesting cases that we're talking
about. And I personally don't see a particular bias one way or
the other way here, but we can discuss it more later. But
the case here is, right, that we're dealing about... the heirs are
dividing it between themselves. And now they want back... and now afterwards
they want back out, and רב נחמן Rav Nachman says no, of
course the court appointed them, it's going to remain binding. So if
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says that when the court does it, it
remains binding, why does he say that we rule like the חכמים
Hachamim and not like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel?
So the גמרא Gemara says there's an obvious difference between how much
an error or when you're prepared to reverse the court's rulings. The
גמרא Gemara says like this: לא קשיא. Lo kashya. הא דטעה הא
דלא טעה. Ha d'to ha d'lo to. In the משנה, Mishnah there
was a clear error. Right? They over and under-sold it by more
than a sixth. So there רב נחמן Rav Nachman: would say no,
there we are going to reverse the court's ruling. The court's ruling
isn't always binding. But if it's a case of
appointing representatives and dividing the estate, there's no error, there might be
an issue of preference, but there's no real error. Okay, if there
was a real error, if I argued for my orphan and I
thought that this piece of land was a steal and worth so
much money and it turns out that I got him something worth
ten percent of a pittance of what everybody else got, maybe we
would be prepared to reassess. Okay, but the reason he's saying we
don't reassess is because they just say they have a preference issue,
it's not a real error. Then we say what the court did
is binding. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי דלא טעה, ei d'lo
to, if they didn't make a mistake, במאי יכולים למחות, b'mai yecholim
limchot, and why does שמואל think that they can object? What are
they objecting to if there was no mistake?
ברוחות, B'ruchot, about directions. I'd rather want one on the sunny side,
I'd rather one closer to town, further from town, whatever the case
is, I like it more in the commercial district, I like it
more in the suburban area, whatever it is. So those are issues
mostly of preference and not the same degree of objective error. Okay,
so now what we have said is, is that you have the
idea in the משנה Mishnah where רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says even when the court makes an objective error, right,
more or less than a sixth, a big mistake, it's still binding.
The חכמים Hachamim say no, it's not binding when it's a big
mistake. And the גמרא Gemara is allowing for the fact that the
court is binding in a case where it's not as much of
an objective error, where there's an issue about like a preference question,
or you could argue that this is better than the other, maybe
it's a little bit of an error, because by the way, the
חכמים Hachamim also say that it's binding when there's a little bit
of an error, up to a sixth. Alright, so is that clear
the differences here, right? That the חכמים Hachamim say yes, it's binding
because of the court and we tolerate a certain amount of error,
but not a huge error. So when רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
it's binding when they appointed the representatives, that's also a case where
there might be preference issues, little bit of an error, but it's
not a huge error. If it's a huge error, then רב נחמן
is going to say it's not binding. Alright, even if it's done
by the court. So now the גמרא Gemara has a story. כי
אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי
Rav Dimi came he said... מעשה ועשה רבי כדברי חכמים. Ma'aseh va'asa
Rebbe k'divrei chachamim. There's a story that רבי Rebbe ruled like the
חכמים Chachamim that they had over or undersold it by a sixth,
and he ruled like the חכמים Chachamim that it was void, and
אמר לפניו amar lefanav so said in front of him פרטא, Parta,
this guy by the name of פרטא, Parta, בנו של רבי אלעזר
בן פרטא, bno shel Rabbi Elazar ben Parta, the son of רבי
אלעזר בן פרטא, Rabbi Elazar ben Parta, בן
בנו ben bno so he was the grandson של רבי פרטא הגדול,
shel Rabbi Parta Hagadol, right, so his grandfather's name was פרטא, Parta,
right, you got it, that's why his father's name was רבי אלעזר
בן פרטא Rabbi Elazar ben Parta and his name was פרטא. Parta.
Okay, anyway, אם כן im ken so he said to רבי, Rebbe,
מה כוח בית דין יפה, ma koach beit din yafeh, if you're
going to void the court's decision when it's more or less than
a sixth, where's the power of the court? וחזר רבי ועשה מעשה
v'chazar Rebbe v'asa ma'aseh so רבי Rebbe reversed his decision and he
left the court's decision standing. Now I have to point out here
that starting here there's going to be an ongoing irony in the
discussion of the גמרא Gemara because notice what just happened. He said
to רבי Rebbe made a פסק, p'sak, okay, we have to reverse
it. Doesn't oh, you can't reverse something the court has done because
where's the power of the court? Oh, you're right, I better reverse
my decision. So, what? Not going to reverse what the court has
done, but we're prepared to reverse the פסק p'sak decision, okay, and
this is going to be an interesting I think parallel discussion that's
going to go on, okay. So איכא דאמרי ika de'amri so, okay,
so where are we? רב ספרא מתני הכי, Rav Safra masni hachi,
here's how רב ספרא Rav Safra taught it. מעשה וביקש רבי לעשות
כדברי חכמים, Ma'aseh uvikeish Rebbe la'asot k'divrei chachamim, רבי Rebbe was about
to rule like the חכמים Chachamim and to say it was void.
אמר לפניו פרטא בנו של רבי אלעזר בן פרטא בן בנו של
רבי פרטא הגדול, Amar lefanav Parta bno shel Rabbi Elazar ben Parta
ben bno shel Rabbi Parta Hagadol, so this פרטא Parta said to
רבי Rebbe before he ruled, he was about to rule, he said
to him, אם כן מה כוח בית דין יפה, im ken ma
koach beit din yafeh, so you can't do that cause then where's
the power of the court? ולא עשה רבי את המעשה v'lo asa
Rebbe et hama'aseh so he didn't rule that way. So why this
second story is better, or at least better, it's less ironic, is
because then רבי Rebbe doesn't reverse himself, right? He catches רבי Rebbe
before he reverses himself. So then it's consistent with the idea that
you don't reverse. But the first story is particularly ironic. In order
to say that the court doesn't reverse itself, I'll have to reverse
myself. Okay, so let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara continues
in this discussion. לימא בהא קמיפלגי. Lema bahai kamifligi. Let's say this
is what they're debating. The two versions of the story. מר סבר
טועה בדבר משנה חוזר ומר סבר אינו חוזר. Mar savar to'eh bidvar
mishna chozer umar savar eino chozer. So here's a question. When a
court errs in a matter of law, not a matter of fact,
does it have to, is the ruling void? And the גמרא Gemara
has different degrees of error. There's an error of בשיקול הדעת, b'shikul
hadaat, a judgment call of law, right, that there is, you know,
precedent or whatever, but it's not black letter law, there's a judgment
call, most people would say that they made the wrong judgment but
it's not black and white wrong. And then there's a case of
טועה בדבר משנה, to'eh bidvar mishna, they made an error in what
we would call black letter law, okay, it's clearly ruled and it's
a clear objective error. And the question is, when you are טועה
בשיקול הדעת to'eh b'shikul hadaat the judgment remains binding. You might have
to pay for the mistake but whatever, but the judgment remains binding.
When you are טועה בדבר משנה to'eh bidvar mishna with black letter
law, then the judgment reverses itself. Now notice the fascinating parallel with
what we've discussed. Certain amount of mistake, up to a sixth, everybody
agrees remains binding, right? When it gets to a certain point that
it's a huge objective mistake, more than a sixth, which most of
us would say is big enough to be an objective mistake, there's
the debate, does it remain binding or not? So if you compare
that's a question of error in fact. What about when you have
a similar issue of error in law? טועה בשיקול הדעת To'eh b'shikul
hadaat remains binding. Once it's a big mistake and טועה בדבר משנה,
to'eh bidvar mishna, black letter law, does it remain binding or not?
Maybe that's what these two versions argue on. מר סבר טועה בדבר
משנה חוזר, Mar savar to'eh bidvar mishna chozer, one says when you
make a mistake in black letter law it reverses. Now the interesting
thing is that this issue of מה כוח בית דין יפה ma
koach beit din yafeh is considered to be דבר משנה, dvar mishna,
like black letter law, cause since when did רבי Rebbe make a
mistake in black letter law? There's a debate in the משנה Mishnah?
whether the court's over-assessment or under-assessment is reversed. So that's a judgment
call, who do you rule like in the משנה? Mishna, So it's
very bizarre that the
גמרא Gemara
calls this a case of דבר משנה, dvar mishna, like black letter
law. רש''י Rashi says, well, because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel gives a
reason for his position, אם כן מה כוח בית דין יפה, im
ken ma koach beit din yafeh, so that's pretty clear that we
should rule that way. But again, to call that, you know, it's
like, okay, you need a שיקול הדעת shikul hadaat to
determine what's שיקול הדעת shikul hadaat and what's דבר משנה. dvar mishna.
Like I know somebody who had a rabbi had written into his
contract that the rabbi is the sole authority on matters of הלכה
halacha and the rabbi gets to decide what's a matter of הלכה.
halacha.
So, you know, you need a שיקול הדעת shikul hadaat to determine
what's שיקול הדעת shikul hadaat and what's דבר משנה. dvar mishna. So
anyway, so number one, we're already deciding that this is דבר משנה.
dvar mishna. Okay. And then the question is, so whether רבי Rebbe
can reverse his own ruling based on whether you're חוזר בדבר משנה
chozer bidvar mishna or not. So
מר סבר חוזר ומר סבר אינו חוזר. mar savar chozer umar savar
eino chozer. The גמרא Gemara says לא דכּולּי עלמא טועה בדבר משנה
חוזר. lo d'kuli alma to'eh bidvar mishna chozer. Everybody would say that
when you make a mistake in black letter law you reverse yourself.
So everybody agree that had רבי Rebbe ruled that way, he would
have reversed himself. The difference is ומר סבר הכי הוה מעשה ומר
סבר הכי הוה מעשה. u’mar savar hachi hava maaseh u’mar savar hachi
hava maaseh. They just had different versions of the story, but it’s
not that they have different versions of what the הלכה halacha would
have been. Everybody agrees that רבי Rebbe would have reversed himself even
had he ruled that way. So now by the way, notice the
irony. What the גמרא Gemara. is doing is, is that basically it
just sounds like this great parallel. When you’re more than a sixth,
an error in fact, a clear error, is it reversible or not?
And we have this great parallel. When you’re more when it’s a
clear objective error in law, do you reverse yourself or not? Right?
And what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that actually when it’s
an error in law, everybody would agree that it gets reversed. And
nevertheless, you might not reverse yourself when it’s an error in fact.
And that’s exactly exactly what happened. רבי Rebbe realized he made an
error in law, he reversed himself. What was his error in law?
His error in law was that when בית דין Beis Din makes
an error in fact, it remains binding. Right? So it’s you gotta
love the irony, but also, you know, it’s an important point, which
is saying that when בית דין Beis Din makes an error in
law, sort of like the idea when a שליח steps out of
their שליחות. shlichus How would a בית דין Beis Din step out
of their authority? The way Michael steps out of his שליחות shlichus
is he undersells my property by a dollar. Okay, that’s how he
stepped out of his שליחות and then it’s not binding. מה כוח
בית דין יפה ma koach beis din yafeh means whenever בית דין
Beis Din. does something, they’re authorized and it’s binding even if they’ve
made a mistake in fact. But, you know when they step out
of their authority, their role? When they’re actually acting outside of the
law. When you’re acting when you’re acting within the law, then whatever
you do is binding even if you made a mistake in terms
of your assessment of the facts. But if you’re acting outside of
the law, then you stopped acting in the capacity of בית דין.
Beis Din So I think again there’s this great parallel between when
the שליח steps outside and when the בית דין Beis Din steps
outside. As long as you’re the בית דין Beis Din. and what
you’re doing is legal, then even mistakes in facts you’re still authorized.
But if you’re טועה בדבר משנה, to’eh bidvar mishnah, then we’ve got
to reverse it because then you’re no longer acting as a בית
דין.
Beis Din Yes. I want to make sure that I’m understanding it
accurately. If if I am assuming it’s obvious that if they they
rule בית דין Beis Din rules on what they think are the
facts... Right. ...so that stands. What if it’s clear that they made
a mistake in facts and then that’s proven afterwards? Are they obligated
to reverse themselves?
No, mistake in fact, that’s the point of מה כוח בית דין
יפה, ma koach beis din yafeh, that stands, it remains standing. But
if they realize they made a mistake in law, then it gets
reversed. I understand. Okay, so that’s exactly this difference: mistake in law
is they’re not authorized, mistake in fact, they’re authorized and it’s binding.
Even if they say
הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beis din hefker, whatever.
Well, no, that’s totally consistent. That’s why a mistake in fact is
binding because...
I mean they’re learning by six, you know, you know what I
mean?
You’re just challenging the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, but this גמרא Gemara
is working within רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Okay.
Now by the way, there’s also an interesting contrast. The גמרא Gemara
a minute ago said לית דחש להא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, leit
dechash le’ha de’Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, we don’t worry about רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, and here the גמרא Gemara is
saying that רבי Rebbe actually ruled like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel and actually to rule otherwise would be טועה בדבר
משנה. to’eh bidvar mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara is giving you very
different messages about how much is it, you know, do we go
like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel or not? Let’s
continue in the גמרא. Gemara Okay. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef,
said רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: אלמנה דזבינה אחריות איתמי. almanah de’zabina achrayus
ayasmi.
Okay, so
if a widow
sells property to collect for her כתובה and then it turns out
that the property was stolen, it did not belong to the estate,
and the guy who bought the property now and it was taken
away from him by the original owners and he wants to be
paid back his purchase price because he bought it off of the
estate, you know who he goes to be paid back his purchase
price to? The estate, not the widow. The widow was selling it
for the estate. The estate owed her the money. If they’ve got
a problem, then they go back to the estate. It was the
estate that was paying her off, that was so somebody’s complaint goes
back to the estate. Okay, see רש״י Rashi also, so here they’re
being nice to the widow. I don’t think it’s a question of
nice or not nice, I think it’s really just figuring out how
to negotiate the different sides.
How do you get that from these words? I’m sorry.
אלמנה דזבינה, Almanah de’zabina, a widow who sells, אחריות, achrayus, the legal
responsibility, which is understood that when you sell land אחריות achrayus means
the responsibility to make good if it was a bad if it
wound up that you weren’t entitled to sell it, that goes back
to the orphans, איתמי. ayasmi. Okay, ובית דין דזבני, u’veis din de’zabni,
now if בית דין Beis Din sells the estate property in order
to pay off the widow’s debt or whatever, and it turns out
that it wasn’t the land, the land wasn’t legally owned by the
estate and the buyers want their money back, אחריות איתמי, achrayus ayasmi,
they also go to the estate. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא דזבינה, peshita de’zabina, of course, I mean it’s the estate’s debt
to the widow and whatever. No, אמר ליה לא צריכא, amar leh
lo tzricha, you’re right, the case of the widow you didn’t need
to say. כי אצטריכא, Ki itztricha, when did you need to say
it? בי דינא, bei dina, when the בית דין Beis din sells.
Now also there, מהו דתימא, mahu detaima, also there, whose responsibility is
it if not the estate? No, I might have thought כל דזבין
מבי דינא, kol de’zabin mi’bei dina, anybody that buys through a court
process, a court-appointed sale,
okay... He assumes that if it's being done by the court then
it's very well known, you know, everybody has heard that this property
is up for sale. If anybody thought that that property was theirs
they would have
come they would have
come to בית דין Beis din and registered a complaint and therefore
maybe he's implicitly waiving his rights
to get reimbursed because maybe he should be assuming
that nobody is ever going to make a claim against him, okay,
and therefore קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that that's not true,
you know, that he might think that it's much less likely somebody
is going to have a claim against him, but he's not waiving
his rights and if there is a claim, he wants his money
back. Okay. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer,
now we get to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל'ס Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's
statement which says אם כן מה כח בית דין יפה, im kein
mah koach beis din yafeh, that even if they make a mistake
and over or underassess, it remains binding. So the גמרא Gemara says
עד כמה? ad kama? So the גמרא Gemara says how far does
this go? The גמרא Gemara assumes that it can't be, you know,
without any limit. So אמר רב הונא בר יהודה אמר רב ששת,
Amar Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar Rav Sheshes, עד פלגא, ad palga,
up to half. Now how do you figure out half, right? So
you know, let's take a look. I mean, you'd think that's an
easy answer, but let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, we taught similarly: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר בית דין שמכרו
שוה מאתים במנה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer beis din shemachru shaveh
masayim bemaneh, if they sold something worth two hundred for a hundred,
או שוה מנה במאתים, o shaveh maneh bemasayim, or a hundred for
two hundred, מכרן קיים, machran kayam, it's valid. So rather than assuming
that the גמרא Gemara means like it means like it doesn't matter
even double, even half, you know, but of course the גמרא Gemara
understands it means precisely, anything more than that would be void. So
if you sell it for less than fifty percent, undersell it for
less than fifty percent of its value, or you oversell it for
more than a hundred, that's why the idea of half is not
so clear, right? So more than a hundred percent, then it is
going to be, then it's going to be void. The גמרא Gemara
assumes it's going to be void although that's not explicit in what
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said.
Okay. אמר אמימר משמיה דרב יוסף, Amar Ameimar mishmei d'Rav Yosef, said
אמימר Ameimar in the name of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, בית דין
שמכרו בלא הכרזה, Beis din shemachru belo hachrazah,
if בית דין Beis din sold without going through this process of
taking out announcements and an open auction process, נעשו כמי שטעו בדבר
משנה וחוזרים. na'asu k'mi sheta'u bidvar mishna vechozrin. Now notice again the
טעו בדבר משנה. ta'u bidvar mishna. Now we've established that it's one
thing to make an error in fact, it's another thing to make
an error in law. So the גמרא Gemara says if they didn't
do the right process, then that's an error in law.
Even if they got the right price?
Even if well, I don't know how you'd know that they got
the right price, but that's a good question. I don't know. But
let's assume that there was some okay. Right, so so you understand
the point here? Which is that it's one thing to say that
they got the facts wrong, but it's another if they didn't do
the right process, then they weren't operating in their authorized capacity, right?
They were only authorized to sell it if they followed the procedures.
They did not go by the procedures and therefore,
it's בטל. Okay. So מכרו נעשו כמי שטעו בדבר משנה וחוזרים,
Machru na'asu k'mi
sheta'u bidvar mishna vechozrin, and it's reversed. So the גמרא Gemara says
נעשו? na'asu? It says as if they made a mistake in a
matter of law? אטו בטעות? Atu b'taus? They definitely made a mistake
in a matter of law. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה,
Mishna שום היתומים שלשים יום, Shum hayesomim shloshim yom,
when you assess the value of orphans' estate to sell it, you
go you do a thirty-day process of open auction and announcement, ושום
ההקדש ששים יום, v'shum hahekdesh shishim yom, and when you're selling property
of הקדש hekdesh sixty days, ומכריזין בבקר ובערב, umachrizin baboker uba'erev, and
you make public announcements morning and evening or late afternoon. אם כן,
Im kein, so you see that you have to do it, it
says you have to make announcements. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
אי מההיא, ei mehahi, if it just said that, הוה אמינא, hava
amina, that's when somebody has been appointed to sell for the orphans,
but not let's say the בית דין themselves. You know, I don't
know, maybe it means that the widow is doing it or something
like that.
אבל בית דין, Aval beis din, I might have thought again that
the power of the court is if the court is directly involved
in the sale, no, then they don't need a process of הכרזה.
hachrazah. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that they do, and if
they don't go through the right process, it's not a valid sale.
So they're losing at least a month then for getting food?
That's true. Well the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that, okay,
because as we said, food you speed up the process, so we'll
see, we're going to get to that in a minute. So the
גמרא says like
this: אייתי רב אשי לאמימר, Eisi Rav Ashi l'Ameimar, so רב אשי
Rav Ashi asks אמימר: Ameimar: שום היתומים שפחתו שתות או הותירו שתות
מכרן בטל. Shum hayesomim shepichsu shtus o hosiru shtus machran batel. הא
שוה בשוה, Ha shaveh beshaveh, so clearly the point of the משנה
Mishna is if they got the right price, מכרן קיים, machran kayam,
so it's valid. Okay now, Michael, actually here's your point, I was
blanking for a moment, the גמרא is actually going to suggest that
if what you're saying is really true, then even if you get
the right price it should be void. So the משנה Mishna? makes
it clear that if you get the right price it's valid, right,
by חידוש. chidush. Okay. But now what's the case of the משנה?
Mishna With or without the process of announcement? So the גמרא says
מאי לאו דלא אכרז? Mai lav d'lo achriz? Presumably the case in
the משנה Mishna is there is no process of announcing, and even
so it's going to remain valid as long as there was not
too much of an over or
undercharge. גמרא says לא בדאכרז, Lo bidachriz, no, the case of the
משנה Mishnah was where there was this
process
of publicizing. How do you know it? דקתני סיפא, Dekatni seifa, the
end of the משנה Mishnah says: אם עשו איגרת ביקורת אפילו מכר
שווה מנה במאתיים או שווה מאתיים במנה מכרן קיים. Im asu igeret
bikoret afilu machar shaveh maneh be'matayim o shaveh matayim be'maneh makhran kayyam.
The end of the משנה Mishnah. says, if you went through the
process of assessing and open auction, it's always binding. So therefore, clearly,
if you do that process, then it's always good. So in the
end, we were talking about without that process. So it's clear that
that's very much פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah So the beginning
of the משנה Mishnah makes it clear even without that process, as
long as you're not too off, it's still going to be binding.
So the גמרא says אלא לעולם
דלא אכרוז. Ela le'olam d'lo achruz. Okay, fine, you're right. The beginning
of the משנה Mishnah is without the process. But nevertheless, I'm not
going to back down from my position. And
I'm going to say there are times where you can get away
without that process, but other times if you don't do the process
it's void. What's the difference? לא קשיא, Lo kashya, even if you
get the right price. כאן בדברים שמכריזין עליהן כאן בדברים שאין מכריזין
עליהן. Kan bidvarim she'makhrizin aleihen kan bidvarim she'ein makhrizin aleihen. There are
some types of things that you do that you have to do
the process
for of publicizing and some that you don't. So in the משנה
Mishnah we're saying that it's valid without a process of publicizing, that
was the types of objects you don't normally do this process of
auction and publicizing. But when you need to do that process, then
it's void without it. What's the difference?
ואלו הן דברים שאין מכריזין עליהן? V'elu hen dvarim she'ein makhrizin aleihen?
What are things you don't do the whole announcement and public auctions
for?
העבדים והמטלטלין והשטרות. Ha'avadim v'ha'metaltelin v'ha'shtarot. Slaves, cattle, and documents of debt.
Why? עבדים טעמא מאי? Avadim ta'ama mai? Why don't you do a
whole month-long process of making a public auction? שמעי וערקי. Shem'ei v'arki.
That the slaves will hear that they're about to be sold and,
I mean, you know, they liked their previous owner, whatever, who knows
who this next person is going to be, so they're going to
escape.
מטלטלין ושטרות, Metaltelin v'shtarot, why don't you do a process of public
auction for cattle and documents? שמא ייגנבו. Shema yignavu. Because everybody is
coming in and doing the whole viewing and they pocket some of
it. You can't pocket land. Okay, so you only do this process
for this public announcement for
land. All right. So the משנה Mishnah that says it's binding without
that process is when you're not dealing with land. So if you're
not dealing with land, how is the widow getting paid for it
for her... the widow only has a lien on land, right? So
right, how is the widow getting paid for her debt if it's
not land? Okay, it's a special case where a lien was placed
even on these other things. So it's a very weird case. Okay,
so the משנה Mishnah that says it's binding without the public auction,
that's when it's not land. But when it is land and you
have to do the public auction, it would not be binding without
that. That's answer number one. Answer number two is, ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it
eima, if you want I'll tell you, כאן במקום שמכריזין כאן במקום
שאין מכריזין. Kan bimkom she'makhrizin kan bimkom she'ein makhrizin.
That there are times when you do a public auction and times
when you don't do a public auction. What does this mean? And
this gets to your point, Michael, about whether you always have to
wait. דאמרי בנהרדעא, D'amri bi'Neharde'a, as they say in נהרדעא, Neharde'a, לכרגא,
L'kharga, when you're talking about a poll tax, when the government wants
its taxes, and if you don't pay your taxes believe me you're
going to be in big trouble, okay, or ולמזוני, U'l'mezonei, the widow
needs her food, okay, or ולקבורה, U'likvura, the guy needs to be
buried and you need to sell the estate for burial. In those
cases where there's an urgency, מזבנינן בלא אכרזתא. Mazbininan belo akhrata. You
sell without public auction. Okay, so therefore you're right, the משנה Mishnah,
has a scenario but actually this could be very much פשט pshat
in the משנה, Mishnah because the משנה Mishnah is about a case
of a widow. Right? So everybody get what we're talking about? I
mean, I know it's a little bit rushed here, but basically is
the claim was without public auction it's always void. The משנה Mishnah
makes it clear that with public auction, no matter what the price
is it's good. Without public auction, it depends on a sixth or
less than a sixth. So it's clear from the משנה Mishnah without
public auction it's valid. How do you explain that? Either you say
it's specific items that don't need public auction, or specific scenarios that
don't need a public auction like she needs to get her food
which is a classic case of the widow wanting to sell the
estate and therefore there's no public auction. So in those cases, I
don't know, in those
cases that's when it still would be valid. Okay, now the גמרא
says: ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, and if you want you could say:
כאן במקום שמכריזין כאן במקום שאין מכריזין. Kan bimkom she'makhrizin kan bimkom
she'ein makhrizin. It depends on not the time, not the objects, but
the place. דאמר רב נחמן, D'amar Rav Nachman, said רב נחמן: מעולם
לא עשו איגרת ביקורת בנהרדעא. Me'olam lo asu igeret bikoret bi'Neharde'a. They
never went through this process of assessment which means public auction in
נהרדעא. Neharde'a. So although you always have to do public auction, in
some places it's off limits. Why is it off limits in נהרדעא?
Neharde'a? סברי מינה משום דבקיאי בשומא. Savri minah mishum d'vaki'ei b'shuma.
Because everybody in נהרדעא Neharde'a were big experts and nobody needed public
auction, everybody could immediately assess the true value. אמר רב יוסף בר
מניומי, Amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi, רב יוסף בר מניומי Rav Yosef
bar Minyumi said: לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרב נחמן... Lidi mifresha li
mineih d'Rav Nachman... It was explained to me in the name of
רב נחמן that here why they don't do public auctions in נהרדעא,
Nehardea, משום דקרו ליה בני אכלי נכסי אחתיחתא, mishum de-karu lei benei
achli nichsei achtechasta,
because people that buy stuff off of public auction, people say, "Yeah,
yeah, yeah, you're the people that gobble up the property of public
auctions," meaning you take advantage of orphans. Stuff is sold at public
auction to pay off the debts of the estate, so people got
a bad reputation. And how do people know I was buying stuff
in public auction? Cause you've been announcing it for the last month,
right? So when you make a big deal and big announcement, then
it's very, you know, nobody wants to buy, or people who do
buy get a bad reputation. But the reality is the property does
have to be sold off. So in some locations for—they made it—it
became a policy not to do public auction. So bottom line what
we're saying is,
משנה makes it clear that without public auction it's still binding. We're
claiming without public auction it's void. The resolution is there are three
scenarios where you don't need public auction: the items, chattel or slaves;
the situations, whether you have to be paying off urgent debts or
the widow has to be—get her מזונות; mezonot; or number three, certain
locations, public auctions are
off-limits. Alright, and now we'll just end. הגמרא Ha-Gemara says like this:
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מטלטלין דייתמי שיימינן להו ומזבינא להו אלתר.
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel metaltelin de-yatmi shamminan le-hu u-mazbinan le-hu altar.
If you have chattel of orphans, which basically are also things that
are like, you know, what's its name, things things that are—I'm looking
for the
word—not permanent, things—temp—not—that's not
the word. Anyway, whatever. I know what it means. It means chattel,
but it also means things that their value could go down. We're
not talking about cars. We're talking about like things that could depreciate
in value also. Anyway, you sell it immediately in order so that
you can get a good price and that it doesn't—and that the
price doesn't—perishable! That was the word, thank you. And so the price
does not—you don't lose—it doesn't lose value. Okay. רב חסדא אמר אבימי
מזבנינן להו ליומי דשוקא.
Rav Chisda amar Avimi
mazbininan le-hu le-yomei de-shuka.
No,
you wait for the market day, even though it'll be a little
less fresh, the fruit, you'll be able to sell it all and
you'll get, you know, it'll be better if you just wait a
few days for the market day. ולא פליגי הא דמקרב שוקא הא
דמרחק שוקא, Ve-lo peligi ha de-mikrav shuka ha de-merachak shuka,
is the market day near or is the market day far away,
right? But so if you've got—anyway, you try to do what can
get you the best price. רב כהנא הוה בידיה שכרא דרב משרשיא
בר חילקאי יתמא. Rav Kahana hava bi-yadei shichra de-Rav Mesharshiya bar Chilkai
yatma.
So רב כהנא Rav Kahana had beer in the—of this רב משרשיא
Rav Mesharshiya who was an orphan, and he was appointed to oversee,
you know, to take care of the value of the estate. שייה
עד ריגלא.
Shayei
ad rigla.
He waited until the רגל regel to sell the beer for the
estate. אמר אע"ג דנפל ביה איצצא, Amar af gav de-nafal beih itzatza,
even though it got a little bit spoiled, not, you know, whatever,
it started souring a little bit by waiting to the רגל, regel,
but מאי זוזי חריפא, mai zuzei charifa, we'll get the money very
quickly, meaning we'll sell it all off, you know, at the time
of the רגל, regel, everybody's buying the beer, everybody's coming to ירושלים
Yerushalayim or whatever, I'll sell off all of it. So it makes
more sense to try to wait then and sell it, even though
it's of a lesser value at that time, because ultimately that's in
the best interests of the estate in order of getting—selling it all
off and getting all the money. Okay, and רש"י Rashi also says
you get cash. You get—you know, you don't—you know, if I sold
it now, everybody would get it—I'd sell it locally and everybody would
put it on a tab, this way I'm going to get all
the money in cash, I'll get a little bit less money cause
it'll have depreciated a little bit in value, but ultimately getting you
all the money in cash is going to be better for the
orphan. רבינא הוה בידיה חמרא דרבינא זוטא יתמא בר אחתיה. Ravina hava
bi-yadei chamra de-Ravina Zuta yatma bar achateih. So רבינא Ravina had in
his possession wine of his nephew, the orphan, and he was appointed
to to—yeah, he was appointed to sell it. ורמי ליה דידיה נמי.
Ve-rami lei de-didei namei. Now he also had his own wine. הוה
קמפיק ליה לסיכרא. Hava kam-afik lei le-Sichra. He was transporting his wine
to this place סיכרא Sichra by ship. אתא לקמיה דרב אשי. Ata
le-kamei de-Rav Ashi. He said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמר ליה
מהו לאמטויי בהדן, amar lei mahu le-amtuyei behadan, should I transport this
guy's wine with mine? Cause it's a good market, I'll get a
good price, but who knows, maybe the ship will sink, so maybe
I shouldn't do it, maybe it's taking too much of a risk.
אמר ליה זיל לא עדיף מדידך, Amar lei zil lo adif mi-didach,
his wine isn't any better than yours. If you're willing to take
that risk with your own wine because of the profit you'll make,
then it's a reasonable risk to take with his wine as well.
Okay, so here it ends also by this issue about—it's interesting to
note we started with the issue of very limited discretion if you're
not the court, right? And here we're dealing with issues again about
you have to assess the situations and have a certain amount of
discretion to make the best judgment of what's going to be in
the best interest of the orphan. And we'll end with that.